Guide to the George Herbert Gray Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Herbert Gray papers
1921-1945
MS 251
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(3 boxes)
Correspondence, surveys, reports, maps, legal documents, printed matter and clippings relating to Gray's work as a planning consultant for the Connecticut State Planning Board and his private work in the field of flood control. The surveys for Connecticut (1921-1940) cover population, state libraries, electricity, and zoning, also specifications for a house in Hamden, Connecticut and material on pollution of the Connecticut River. Planning data is also included for flood control in Ohio, for the Huron Valley in Michigan and for the New England region.
Gray, George Herbert, 1874-1945
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
These papers of George Herbert Gray consist entirely of subject files kept during the 1930s while Gray worked for various Connecticut and federal planning agencies, in particular the Connecticut State Planning Board. The files are arranged alphabetically by projects and topics in Gray's original order, and contain approximately 375 letters, memoranda, maps, printed matter, and other papers. Correspondents include a variety of federal, state, and local government offices and officials. Among the topics covered are floods and flood control, town and state planning projects, water legislation and zoning, and rural zoning.
These papers were given to Yale University in 1946 by Mrs. George H. Gray.
Biographical / Historical
Consultant in architecture and city planning; A.B., Johns Hopkins, 1895; studied architecture in New York & Paris, 1896-1907; practicing architect, 1906-1925, architect and city planner since 1925; head of Dept. of City Planning, Columbia, 1920-1923.
Architecture, Domestic -- Designs and plans; City planning -- Connecticut; Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; Flood control -- Ohio; Connecticut River; Connecticut -- Social conditions; New Haven (Conn.); City planners; Gray, George Herbert, 1874-1945; Connecticut. State Planning Board
- Inventory
  - Connecticut
    - Area, 1928-1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ashford and Essex, subsistence homesteads, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Electrical survey, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Government, 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Population, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - State library survey and educational, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - State school system, 1921, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Work -Hamden, 44 Morse St., 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Connecticut Refuse Disposal (Gen. Sanford H. Wadhams, director of Conn. State Water Commission), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Connecticut River
    - Pollution, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Zoning, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    General note
    See also: Box 3
  - Conservation
    - General, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Game and wildlife, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Eliot, Charles William 2nd (assistant executive officer of the National Resources Board), 1934-1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 14 - 19)
  - Flood, 1936-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 20 - 23)
  - Flood control, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Flooded cities, 1937-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 25 - 28)
  - Forests, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Forests and town parks, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Housing, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Housing Authority, 1935-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Huron Valley (Michigan) Improvement Plan, 1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Land use, 1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    See also: Box 3 Folder 74 - 75
  - Mapping technique, 1934-1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Maps
    - General, 1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Comparative data, 1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Drafting Force, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Ohio flood Control Congress, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Places of historic and scenic interest, 1933-1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 40 - 42)
  - Planning
    - General, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - New England Regional Board Meetings, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Regional Association, Inc., 1934 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Town, 1933-1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 46 - 47)
    - Town; letters to selectment, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Planning Board
    - Connecticut State, 1933-1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 49 - 52)
    - Publicity for Connecticut state, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Fleming, Phillip B. (executive officer of Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works), 1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 54 - 55)
  - Recreation, 1934, 1937, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Roads: Connecticut highways, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Roads and roadsides, Connecticut, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Slate, William L. (Chairman, Governor's Planning Board, Connecticut), 1934 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Transportation, 1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Water legislation: John B. Gates (research investigator), 1934, undated (Box 3, Folder 61 - 63)
  - Waters (Box 3)
    - Connecticut, 1934-1936 (Box 3, Folder 64 - 66)
    - Control of floods and pollution, 1934-1938, undated (Box 3, Folder 67 - 70)
    - Reconnaissance, 1934-1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 71 - 73)
    - Zoning, 1935-1940 (Box 3, Folder 74 - 75)
  - Zoning, rural, 1930-1936 (Box 3, Folder 76 - 81)
  - Zoning and building codes, 1938-1945, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)